welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
hi everyone I'm sama Berea and today
I'll be talking about institutional
reform of government the usual way this
is discussed is very narrow
it's very policy focused sometimes it's
focused on concrete changes to
literature or establishing the
intellectual case for something other
times it's framed in terms of electoral
politics and electoral coalition's I
think both of these approaches are
deeply flawed and not how the most
meaningful change happens in government
I think that it's much less useful to
think of government as a unitary object
as a unitary system and more is a
collection of interdependent systems
right if we think of government is
strictly unitary
then something like modern Britain makes
no sense at all it's a parliamentary
democracy yet it doesn't have a written
constitution it's clearly forming some
sort of Republican representative system
it's a crown monarchy it's a system
where the elected officials though can't
really fire anyone that's sufficiently
senior in the civil service so instead
of thinking of modern Britain as a
republic a monarchy a democracy or a
bureaucracy it's best to think of the
government as a bunch of layered systems
all on top of each other with different
bases of legitimacy and different modes
of operation stuff that's only very
lightly touched by political theory but
mostly encoded in practice mostly coded
coded in precedent and sometimes a
little bit coded by the particular
convenience of key politicians if you
think that it's all discourse you might
waste your time with policy papers and
if you think it's all politics you might
waste all your time boosting a
particular politician and then being
surprised when they necessarily don't do
what they promised to do because often
what they promise to do is impossible
either personally politically impossible
impossible for their wider coalition or
just impossible for the kind of
organization that they've inherited so
thinking of government as several
different institutions as layers of
social technology clarifies how Britain
can both have you know a functioning
dynasty in a way with Queen Elizabeth
being the representative of that dynasty
yet having democratic elements yet
fundamentally still being mostly
dominated by the civil service as such
with the civil service itself not being
necessarily even you know overbearing or
tyrannical as some narratives might
propose which is doing a very narrow job
like a narrow artificial intelligence or
a piece of software so this layering of
social technologies proposes then that
the best way to reform government is to
produce a new government institution or
several that operate on different
principles than the existing
institutions in government yet are
endorsed by the other institutions of
government so when you mix in multiple
agencies into the same interacting
system different agencies come up on top
for example it's an interesting question
and now and maybe look at a historical
example at like you know a more
authoritarian system than what modern
Britain is or what modern the modern
u.s. is in the Soviet Union the key
political power struggle was between the
Communist Party in the KGB it was not
between the Communist Party and the
people or even the Communist Party and
the kulaks right the kulaks were
scapegoats there were wealthy farmers
but they obviously like you know
couldn't engage in industrial warfare
even if they didn't like communism as
such so this key struggle happened
because the KGB as such had the ability
to keep secrets from the Communist Party
as such and in fact kept some secret
successfully the KGB had an agreement
with the East German Stasi to in case of
change in civilian government in East
Germany have the Stasi overthrow the
East German government note the East
German civilian government was a
communist government right Communist
Party officials but the party was
organized along different lines than the
KGB itself even when the party used the
KGB as their own instrument right
one of the keynotes here to consider is
that you know Stalin most of Stalin's
foes were other Communist Party
officials so Stalin perhaps his best
modeled as someone that is a tyrannical
leader using an intelligence agency to
subdue what otherwise would be be a sort
of like committee based party
bureaucracy and if you look at China
today
China's you know greatest threat the
greatest threat that the Chinese
Communist Party is not some sort of
western-style liberal democratic
revolution it will be a military coup
from the People's Liberation Army which
means that they're incentivized in
important ways to disrupt the People's
Liberation Army even while on the other
hand they're incentivized to make it
very formidable and powerful in order to
say challenge the US on the world stage
or more generously provide for Chinese
security and Intel you know and
territorial integrity so what I'm
sketching out here is that if you
interleave different systems they will
come into conflict with each other and
sometimes route past each other so when
I say that you produce a new government
institution that is accepted by current
government institutions and has to be
endorsed by them I'm not saying
compromise with them it's possible to
produce the government institution that
in terms of power or authority or
influence completely displaces the
previous ones either for the better or
for the worse and the key distinction
between this and a revolution is that a
revolution asserts that there is a new
government
it makes the legal case that we are a
distinct entity a distinct system from
the previous one you can have what is a
revolution in substance without ever
having a rebel a revolution on paper and
that's one of the reasons why you know
while I feel that say you know political
theory and written constitutions and all
these methods are valuable and useful
they ultimately are downstream from
these institutional realities the real
Constitution of the United States
changed massively once you added the FBI
or you added the IRS or you
that the Federal Reserve and it changed
massively when the ministry you know the
Department of War in the Department of
Peace you know the State Department and
what used to be called the Department of
War no longer shared a single building
because if you have then the Pentagon
and the State Department is too massive
bureaucracies where people don't run
into each other because they live in the
same building and work in the same
building you can have a more
schizophrenic foreign policy which
basically each one of these institutions
is carrying out a slightly different
international agenda right so something
even when the paper reality doesn't
change as much might still cause a
massive policy shift decades down the
line out if something as trivial as like
changing the physical space where it's
based okay so this is very theoretical
it's a very broad-based but I wanted to
share some of this basic theory and
basic approach here where it proposes
that creating new institutions
completely new ones is the best way to
reform existing systems and it's best to
not propose a strong break with the old
system but still have the firm
expectation of completely altering the
old system cool so would like to hear
questions now so most of you know the
drill here so if you want to ask a
question go ahead and put it in the chat
and then I will call your name and you
can Ameet yourself and ask your question
and just initially here I'll start us
off so Sam oh I'm wondering in recent
history in the United States do you see
that this kind of hidden revolution or
shift of the guard has happened in any
particular way that may be coming to
light in in this current crisis hmm well
I think in the 20th century the u.s. had
several shifts and changes in what the
system is right I think that obviously
the New Deal is the most well-known one
right where FDR you know FDR was
president for life
though we didn't think of him as
president for life right but when
someone has four terms in office
it's the structural advantages to
re-election just become overwhelming
so it's his health rather than any sort
of failure during an election that
secures that position I think that there
was a massive shift in power towards US
intelligence post-world War two so I
think that you know this was stuff that
was shown in the church committee papers
in the 1970s where say the role of the
FBI I got went far into the domain of
regulating political and social life you
know wiretapping MLK you know you're a
wiretap MLK and you wiretap the KKK it's
not because you're picking a side it's
because your objective is a little bit
amoral your objective is continuing
preservation of the system and stability
right and then you you wiretap them and
you sometimes try to blackmail them and
you actively interfere in things that
are relevant to shaping domestic
politics other stuff like this is say
operation Mockingbird and so on I do
think the sense making of the
Intelligence Agency's broke down over
time where you know the intelligence
world of the early 2000s is in a way far
less potent politically than the
intelligence world of the 1960s in fact
makes mistakes that it really shouldn't
have made I think another big change has
been the empowerment of the presidency
and the weakening of the President
himself now I'm not going to comment on
Trump because he's a strange phenomena
is difficult to understand but if we
compared the power of the presidency all
of these extended bureaucracies around
the White House in 2000
in 1950 in 2000 it's actually I think
more powerful but if we could compare
President Eisenhower to you know Bill
Clinton I think Eisenhower is more
personally powerful right so there's an
unacknowledged Rauf of a growth of a
permanent executive in a way another
thing is the weakening of Congress
Congress has over the past 50 years
basically lost the ability to produce
constitutional amendments it's lost the
ability to make committees or
commissions that are more than just for
show but genuine oversight over other
branches of government
there's finally also been a change in
the Supreme Court where the Supreme
Court seems to have evolved into a
legislative Oregon so in a way Supreme
Court influences the substance of laws
far more than Congress does at this
point Congress at this point is
formalizing and putting in motion
suggestions that were worked out outside
of Congress right it's no longer a
deliberative body so in a way it's very
ceremonial and I think we're starting to
treat it as very ceremonial this is why
people get you know so much more excited
over presidential elections than they do
over you know congressional
congressional races I this was that sort
of the question that I managed to answer
the question and the way you are
interested foreign institutions to kind
of like interweave and shift things over
time do you see maybe have you seen the
activity on Twitter and other social
media talking about States a lying to
coordinate during during the Kogan kind
of relief process and reopening the
economy is that a potential move in that
direction we're like states coordinating
and starting to create their own
institutions within regional within the
realm of regional concerns as being a
kind of move from a large structured
federal institution to more localized
influence I think it's plausible that
will be a move in that direction the key
thing to note here is that the United
States if you look at you know the 50 or
so states that it has not counting
various territories and tribal units and
so on where the tribal governments are
supposed to be independent from the
states and important ways and so on any
one of them compared to the federal
government has a miniscule fraction of
wealth GDP a or organizational capacity
right a compact of several states can
have far more power on the other hand
though I think the US has this very
massive and strong press
then against unilateral secession so if
a US state holds referendum and declares
independence after a successful
referendum and the federal government
refuses to leave while the state is not
really independent is it right as long
as the military doesn't leave and if the
state tries to make the federal
government leave the federal government
steps steps right back in now secession
is an extreme state you might think that
this doesn't have consequences
downstream for more normal political
States lower energy political states
rather than high energy political states
but it's straight for really does right
this kind of capacity for political
violence is unfortunately one of the
main factors in shaping everyday
politics right there is contrary
consequences that translate from that
extreme hypothetical all the way to more
mundane circumstances and one of them is
that if the federal government wants to
enforce a law in your territory it will
be able to enforce a law in your
territory and as a stage you can't
really opt out of laws that the federal
government has decided it will not allow
you topped out of so I think that
federal the federal the supremacy of the
federal structure won't go away I think
there is the possibility though that
compacts of states could start
functioning as bigger blocks so if you
have California plus a few more states
you know that's a few percentage points
of the economy or if you have New York
plus some neighboring states that's
several percentage points of the economy
and they can coordinate with each other
honest a federal level to push
acceptance to push the federal
government to accept and stamp things in
various ways you know in a sense more
closer to what the original idea was
between states and the federal structure
but over time the federal structure
became very strong the states became
very weak the key flaw here is that
these state compacts they're not
informed on anything like the basis of
popular sovereignty or popular mandate
so right now if you told people that
California
gonna do things the californian way and
Texas is gonna do things the Texas Way
that has some weight but if you said the
West Coast is gonna do things its its
own way that's already weaker and if you
say the 12 state compact is gonna do
things its way that's just half carries
no weight at all no weight and
legitimacy right so the governor has
done very quickly overstep and start
singing illegitimate there's an
interesting dance here where I think
that there is deferral of responsibility
with regard to opening up the economy
happening so I wonder whether the
governors are just being asked to be the
bag holders right the people who you
know tails tails they lose heads they
lose right if they reopen the economy
too late economic damage to the state is
significant if they reopen too soon and
they're loved that a lot of people die
and is then seen as the problem of these
governors rather than the problem of the
federal government as a whole so I
suspect this as a it's it's convenient
for the federal government to have the
states take the fall on this one so yeah
I would expect a limited consequence I
could see say the West Coast states in
particular having shared economic
interests and persisting in
collaboration past this window of the
next year or two when the kovat crisis
readjusts to a new and different normal
sure sure
thank you for speaking with us today Sam
well I'm curious whether you see any
possibilities in in the near term in the
next couple of years
anywhere in the world where an alliance
between sympathetic forces in in state
institutions or the bureaucracy and a
movement of grassroot participatory
democracy movements could form new
institutions which shift the political
you know realistically shift the
political economy of of state
and historically of what are the closest
analogs of any yeah I think that there's
always the potential for this right the
key potential here is there is a massive
amount of legitimacy that you know
genuine widespread consciousness or
grassroots supports support offers it
just doesn't build that much so it
legitimizes a lot but it in itself does
not build that much because the sort of
like machinery of a new structure is
very intricate and it's very difficult
to translate into you know slogan
shouted in the streets I think that you
know the Yellow Jackets and France were
an interesting example of that fizzling
out where they're still protesting or in
fact protesting this whole time the
protests were quite serious quite well
organized and the French government
essentially ignored it or dispersed the
protests as such they have no strong
support in the French state itself so
the result is that it's mostly fizzling
now and their complaints they're very
genuine complaints they're real
complaints about the state of France's
economy in society how its feeling more
and more hopeless over time but it's not
being translated into something that has
a powerful formula when I look at the
institutional landscape around the world
I think that I am most optimistic about
reform in Spain ironically where Spain
is both fragile and hurting very badly
right now but might have a potential for
a functional rather than dysfunctional
devolution now a dysfunctional
devolution is something like modern-day
Bosnia which after the breakup of the
yugoslavia virile government is
internally divided into Bosnia and
Herzegovina rather the sort of like the
Serbian part and in the Croatian and
Muslim part it has duplicate structures
going through the whole government
including multiple presidents multiple
police forces and the problem is it's
very much of the top
Percy right Vito as in everyone can
block everything and then nothing can
get done because everyone's blocking
these choices and is rightfully
suspicious of these other government
entities so that was an example of a
compromise that brought peace but was a
dysfunctional compromise and today you
know Bosnia is less economically
developed in either Serbia or Croatia
and has higher rates of corruption and
shorter lifespans and so on if Spain
acquires a federalist structure of some
kind where there's autonomous
self-governance along these religious
communities as are these uh
national communities they're all you
know they're mostly Catholic right so
it's not the same situation as in Bosnia
where people the nationalities match up
with the religion right where you know
in Bosnia if you're if you're Orthodox
you ended up identifying a Serbian if
you were Catholic or from Catholic
family ended up identifying an equation
and if you were must them while you
identified as Muslim even though that's
not you know proper nationality in a
classical sense and you still were
speaking in fact a Slavic language and
basically the same Slavic language is
the Croatian of them the Serbians for
speaking that's a stronger analogue to
say perhaps northern island Ireland and
what's happening in Spain is these
languages are legitimately different
especially say the Basque language is
not even a Romance language but the
reason why I expect that there might be
positive potential there is because
there are multiple important cities
there's not just Madrid there's
Barcelona there multiple different
economies there right and once you can
have a political economy that's better
suited to the natural conditions of an
area and if security is not compromised
that might result in notably better
government locally so again Spain has
positive potential I think Britain has
positive potential it's not actualizing
it but because Britain will be now
forced to do something that's different
than what the rest of the European Union
is doing I'm hoping it becomes more
creative rather than less so instead of
converging with the US
instead of converging with Europe it's
going to look at Europe and be like
while we're distinct we haven't yet
decided what it means to be distinct but
let's try to do a few things differently
the key reason I'm less optimistic about
Britain than about Spain is that the
urban centers where elites live and
institutions live are more concentrated
in Britain than they are in Spain in
Britain it's basically just London its
London and the rest well whenever it's X
and the rest it means the rest are an
amalgamation and don't necessarily have
common interests or common resources or
common organization or common social
circles to be able to pull their own
weight
now I know let's say pull their own side
of the tug of war that's better because
pull their own weight already implies
this strange sort of economic
self-sufficiency that's not clear that
exists anywhere today I'm also
optimistic about the long-term
trajectory of Poland I'm not sure
whether that's I think that's a state
that's becoming a highly functional
centralized state so again it has some
possibility of multiple large cities so
if I were to look around the world
beyond Europe I think in the u.s. I'm
not seeing that much evidence of like
governmental reform in the near future
or even populist movements that could
have any sort of things sort of impact
for popular movements I think there is
some possibility for positive change in
South Asia in particular in Southeast
Asia I suspect that there is positive
change possibly open even in a place
like Hong Kong despite everything I do
think that in the aftermath of the
Kovach crisis the status quo is
preserved and the status quo allows for
some local government and as the rest of
China becomes wealthier if Hong Kong
wishes to remain distinct but still part
of China it has to find something
structurally different from what it's
offering now and there was a lot of
energy there but very little
institutional support right but the
energy was definitely there
for something different now I'm not
condoning or condemning anything that
happened in the protest I'm just noting
the raw energy level where the energy
level is best thought of as a function
of a politically engaged populace Plus
grassroots organizing plus the resources
to enable grassroots organizing so
that's kind of what generated this list
so Spain Britain maybe Hong Kong
maybe Poland the Poland seems more
functional centralized rather than
functional decentralized I think that if
I if I if there were more of a civil
society in Saudi Arabia that could
actually become a very interesting
society post-oil but I don't think it
will be so all these interesting
governance experiments where possibly
could see a different political economy
emerge
I'm already presuming they have to be
rich and I'm presuming they have to be
rich or at least be large if not rich in
order to not be immediately integrated
into whatever new system exists locally
right if you're experimenting with a
different socio-economic stack it has to
be it has to have the economies of scale
to at least be capable of being a viable
alternative to whatever the prevailing
paradigm is now whether it's like you
know Chinese capitalism or
european-style welfare market stuff or
american-style welfare market capitalism
stuff it has to be large enough to stand
on its own because otherwise those
countries will use economic weight to
terraform you to be more similar to
themselves so why would a strong
economically powerful trade partner want
to change your political culture in your
political economy to be more similar to
its own well so that it's elites feel
more comfortable doing business in your
country I think that's been one of the
big stories of human history I think oh
if you have any follow-up questions I
think you asked a great question I hope
I managed to answer it I know you did a
great job and I guess what just to carry
on with what you were saying you have to
be large enough I guess one of the one
of the models that was quite unusual is
the role hava through a java movement I
guess and the Kurds that they were
trying to do this
libertarian socialist sort of democratic
confederalism with citizen assemblies
and people's assemblies and stuff like
that and they've been kind of an
inspiration for a lot of you know the
igni mottos and in Spain and many of its
movements around the world and I'm
guessing they're they don't have a lot
of potential because they don't have
that they don't have that they don't
have that much weight so they're there
they they get influenced too much by the
forces around them is that is that your
analysis there oh yeah and note that for
the Kurds themselves well you know they
have impressive organization impressive
military capacity a very good method of
using the oil money to Jenner to
generate some prosperity they managed to
go as far as they could because of a
geopolitical circumstance right of a
collapsing Iraq of a failing Syria of a
failing Syria that was pushed by the US
as well and they have very potent
enemies right they haven't made much
progress in say Turkey
even though arguably Kurds are the most
oppressed in Turkey right Isis was worse
than than that but Turkey is definitely
worse than say the secular Syrian
government or the current set up in Iraq
or even their situation in Iran honestly
you know the work for the Kurdish
Workers Party and so on and stuff like
that so there are geopolitical
circumstances where you can exist on the
border of multiple systems arguably
Singapore's initial prosperity and
viability as a city state a city state
in an era of industrial Titans only
happened you know this was the 20th
century right like the Soviet Union
China the United States these are
industrial behemoth these are like the
kind of you know leviathans that won
World War two or lost World War two
right some of them lost some of them won
these are not city-states and Singapore
could exist because of the Cold War I'm
just gonna propose that it would not
have developed as an independent
fragment and even then Singapore is
deeply is both deeply so to be
compatible with the Anglosphere and
angles for commercial and cultural norms
he
if it takes its own political approach
that's again like this kind of very
civil service very executive branch
oriented city government so yeah that's
that's what I say you can actually have
a smaller or poorer country succeeded
this but they have to have very
favorable geopolitical conditions where
the great powers are balanced against
each other in some way so in a way you
know what we're returning to a
multipolar world with China and the u.s.
like China in the US will remain the
world's number one and number two
economy probably for the rest of my life
so this actually means that on the
border between the two and their spheres
of influence that's where I would also
look for interesting experiments and new
political economies and governments not
because they're strong enough to
challenge either China or the US or to
rip off all their influence but because
they can balance them in such a way that
local uniqueness persists and can be
even further developed to new prosperity
or better ecological balance or more
social cohesion or higher higher
happiness
honestly like these are goals beyond
just economic ones adjusted some size of
economy isn't an industrial era
necessary to maintain independence I'm
not saying that the economic growth is
in itself a name to itself thank you
very much I'm very happy to take more
questions and I think something that's
showing up in what you're talking about
and it seems to be a theme with a lot of
your work is how different institutions
operate at different scales and if so I
mean I think my question is like what is
the rule of scale in the ability for
institutions to change over time and
become more regionally effective
I think scale is always a matter of well
there's a there's a very serious
principle that's also a little bit of a
joke that people are always promoted to
the level of their incompetence I think
institutions always scale beyond where
they work best they overshoot right so
the largest extent of the Roman Empire
isn't when the Roman Empire is working
best it's when all of the investments
from when it was working best come in
when that harvest is in of that seed
corn that was planted long ago and I
think the same happened with the u.s. I
don't think the u.s. worked the best
ever in 1991 but 1991 was probably the
zenith of its global influence and then
similarly I think for non-state
organizations such as the Catholic
Church of we're talking about
large-scale stuff it's like you know 1
billion believers at least in theory and
representatives everywhere and almost
Peres States status right observers in
the United Nations with embassies around
the world the ability to set their own
laws and all of that arguably
overshooting what is optimally needed
for the preservation of a particular
religious teaching so I think it's often
the case that as you scale from
individual to small group to distributed
group to hierarchical group to
coalition's of hierarchical and
distributed groups to coalition's of
those two systems and coordination
protocols at the final level when
there's not even any organizational
connection it's just an alliance of
organizations individuals that do things
the same way the right way and ourself
reflectively you know collaborating on
extending that terraforming process on
the world there is a way in which the
later stages harness the previous stages
right so the resources are accumulated
by a previous stage might then be used
by a different or new stage of social
technology so the kind of accumulation
you might see
arising out of a priestly class in the
ancient agricultural world may then be
used to fund an army or build walls
around the temple and some other
residential areas and then suddenly what
used to be this kind of religious
ceremonial site has acquired the capital
that is used by a different social
system an army and movement of people
control type so a walled city state and
that's sort of the Sumerian city-state
it's clearly a transition from one form
to another that retains the previous
form where the previous form enabled the
kind of material and social accumulation
that were the starting capital in a way
of the next one and I think something
very similar happened with the modern
state where the initial impetus for the
modern state was just like you know
absolutist monarchies of the 17th and
18th century where they wanted to firmly
get in control of any sort of powerful
local feudal powers that might have
remained and they partnered up with a
rising middle class because they figured
out how to tax a rising middle class I'm
a rising bourgeois class in the
Industrial Revolution but then
eventually the absolute monarchy part of
that big structure became obsolete and
was just replaced and axed right and in
many cases literally guillotine right so
there is a there is an interesting way
in which social technologies can lead to
their own opposites if they produce the
material and social preconditions for
their successor and if so there's
another if they're if the new structure
has an active interest in delegitimizing
the old one rather than a mulligan
aiding with it this is perhaps still
like relatively abstract but I would say
that the coordination of people and
large numbers of people to do certain
things or to not do certain things is
like the central challenge of history
almost and we can look at history as the
unfolding of different kinds of social
technology that are actually
prerequisites for material technology
you know I think there is a big
difference between Karen steam engine
and watts
steam engine in engineering here on
living in ancient Alexandria in ancient
Greece sorry ancient Alexandria in the
ancient Greek world
it's what today would be Egypt obviously
and James walked you know living in
Britain in this period of the 17th the
18th century 19th century but the
biggest difference honestly is that
there is a economic use for the steam
engine right there's not like it has to
compete with relatively abundant and
cheap human labor it's actually the case
that you know there is no disposable
human labor at least in that part of
Britain itself the workers sure but
they're no slaves so I think many
material technologies actually have
hidden social technology prerequisites
and I think the material artifacts are
visible you know so the Roman aqueducts
are far more visible than the culture
that was needed to have large urban
populations because without large urban
populations there's no need to deliver
that quantity of water has no reason to
maintain the aqueducts and similarly
when we look at these artifacts of
modern industrial society I don't you
know a jet a jet a jet engine or a
rocket or a computer I don't think we
actually fully understand all the social
technologies in this stack I think we're
not fully self-aware as a civilization I
think we don't fully understand how we
work so I think political science
economics anthropology all of this has
been insufficient to describe to
ourselves what we are and that might
even be in principle impossible because
if a society you know if bodies of
knowledge in a society fully understand
what the society is its society
reflecting on itself it's already become
something more complex jumps through the
process of reflecting on itself thank
you I have a question that I was asked
to read out for you so this is from
Ernesto thank you for your question what
is the solution for minimizing
corruption and governance and what is
the most effective way to implement
transparency and accountability
it's a difficult question I think
there's no Universal answer I think it
really depends strongly on local
incentives it's um
it's very interesting that I think that
individual accountability plays a
significant role but bureaucrats are
always very good shielding themselves
from individual accountability I think a
preference for overt action rather than
covert action is perhaps best so in an
interesting and paradoxical way having
maximally idealist views of what is
legitimate government so as a society
you have maximally idealist views as to
what is a legitimate government then you
are incentivizing the government to hide
anything that's less than ideal so in an
interesting way you are demanding to be
lied to and it's fairly easy to lie to
the population unfortunately right
that's one of the big problems I think
with nineteen and twentieth century
government is that it's possible to
manage public opinion sometimes it's
easier to manage public opinion in this
imagined managed physical reality right
it's easier for China perhaps to censor
the outcome of an earthquake in a region
rather than admit that you know
emergency responses were bad and that
the construction codes were shoddy and
it actually there were a bunch of
casualties this happened a few years ago
I forget which Chinese province but the
best estimates we have suggest notably
higher death told and what was reported
domestically still from the perspective
of you know nine hundred and fifty
million Chinese who were not in that one
province that 50 or maybe 5 million
people province that's a completely
plausible story and that's just the
truth of how things are so I think that
a culture that understands the
imperfection of government and a culture
that values personal integrity and
selects actively for people will succeed
this profession and accrue rewards if
they have personal integrity and intend
to communicate to the public I think
that's a fairly strong combination and
it's can be implemented in many
different ways and in different
cultural contacts right if I wanted to
push more towards honest government in
let's call it let's say 17th century
Germany appealing to Christian virtues
of the rulers might not be too terrible
a stratagem because a lot of them were
probably personally believing Christians
who are tactically avoiding in their own
awareness how the reality of their
government is incompatible with the
principles they believe every Sunday
winter at mass and then as long as this
doesn't cause then the elite as a whole
to be less Christian in that context
that's positive now if you espoused
right about Christian values in the u.s.
today
I don't think that necessarily results
in a better government so that's what it
that's just an illustration not pro or
anti Christianity just an illustration
of how situationally a situationally
dependent the answer to that question is
right like in an interesting way this
the perspective that you know the
government is mostly a reflection of
processes might lead to better outcomes
somewhat you know people might focus on
processes somewhat more they might think
less of personalities and more of
organizations on the other end though on
the other side though it's very easy to
hide something through obscurity so in
order to make a government transparent
you have to make it comprehensible to
make it comprehensible it has to be
relatively simple to have it be
relatively simple and not merely
pretending to be relatively simple then
it has to be both simple and quite
effective otherwise it will be a complex
beast pretending to be simple pretending
giving you like a false you know almost
simulation of how your government works
I also think that day to day oversight
of the government is very difficult but
I do think that you can have societies
where people have enough socio-economic
leisure that they can broad in broad
strokes check in into the functioning of
government say once every
few years and once every year you need
than a culture where people are not
following a 24-hour news cycle but are
instead reading books and they have just
as a normal middle-class person you
might have a strong interest in the
functioning and activities of the IRS
it's not everyone checking to the IRS or
check into the NBA
it's that enough people check into the
FDA and talk about it and have social
circles around it and have a secure
enough job that they can afford books
about it or can afford travel and it's
considered acceptable for them to
literally email in with questions or
Freedom of Information Act requests and
that then produces a demand for
something that's notably more difficult
to fake right and I think that this
direct casual culture of citizen
interest in the true fundamentals of
government and governance is very tricky
and difficult to maintain I think we
don't have it because it very naturally
gets displaced by debates about
personality and debates about the new
cycle and the new cycle chains you to a
memory that from a historical
perspective might as well be goldfish
memory you don't remember what happened
three months ago like to the first
approximation I think people do not
remember what was politically relevant
three months ago
and that's that's really it's terrible
right so to try to restate everything
I've said in like a neat concise part
government has to be relatively simple
it has to be incentivized towards
honesty and the personal social
incentives of the people in government
have to be aligned with this
institutional incentive honesty and
finally there has to be enough of a
leisure class that people just as a
hobby go and think about institutions
and then talk about it relatively freely
and then this can be implemented in many
different ways do you think that's
something like that Jubilee or ubi might
create the possibility for a leisure
class to emerge within like a complex
society like the United States that
would maybe create the possibility for a
citizen on kind of interest in the
functioning of governance that might
create a new incentive structure yeah I
think that a debt Jubilee is the better
approach because I think ubi is
something that it's it's very expensive
to be poor so if you gave the poor more
money on their bank account it helps
them as individuals but over time it
just incentivizes everyone to make it
even more expensive to be poor so in a
weird way if say you are living in San
Francisco and you know there's massive
demand to live in San Francisco and
you've added to everyone's bank accounts
$1,000 a month for example it just means
the rents go up in San Francisco
it doesn't actually help anyone live in
San Francisco and access the economic
activities of San Francisco now on the
margin this might not be true of like
you know a city where the supply of
housing and the demand for housing are
more balanced and I also think that the
health costs would rise to take
advantage of this because currently I
think the I'm grossly simplifying so
please forgive this gross simplification
the the health care system in the US
legally obliges various private entities
to take care of the poor so if you give
the poor more money well they're just
gonna charge them more they're legally
obliged to provide them service whether
or not they're charging them more and
that can eat up a significant chunk of
the ubi as well meanwhile debt debt on
the other hand is much better because in
the u.s. there's an unacknowledged
social control structure you know called
your credit score it's a credit score
it's not a social credit score but it
might as well be it's certainly
influenced by everything you read online
because your data is sold around
promiscuously right what you're buying
on Amazon is like information that's
sold on sold everywhere
and also factors into this mysterious
stuff that feeds into you know your
credit ratings and so on and the credit
ratings influence where you can live and
currently I think the job opportunities
for the few remaining upwardly mobile or
at least jobs that don't necessitate
downward mobility those few jobs are
super geographically gated they only
exist in something like 20 or 30
American cities so even for generous
include the second-tier cities right
like Austin or Seattle so I'm not even
talking here about San Francisco in New
York I don't think there's much
happening out of the top 30 or 40 cities
in the u.s. so you might then alleviate
the plight of people who are healthy but
are primarily held down by rent I think
that's what UVI achieves but you don't
alleviate the plight of the old very
young people who want to have children
people with medical conditions people
with frankly also addictions mental
health issues right like the social
disaster related to the opioid crisis
and basically casual use of uppers and
downers in all parts of American society
to manage mood you know either legal or
illegal so here I'm not actually making
a distinction between adderall and weed
or wheat and heroine or alcohol or
tobacco and all of this it's just the
fact that people are using a lot of
their discretionary spending to regulate
their own move and this sometimes
produces addictions which are complex
social and biological phenomena so it's
not really that straightforward and
these addictions then produce health
side effects with needs which need to be
treated which are super expensive to
treat so I think there it produces then
a class of people who are young
relatively healthy not depressed who
couldn't afford rent in a third-tier
City who can now afford rent in a
third-tier City I think that's
insufficient to be a leisure class at a
high enough level of education on the
other end though debt Jubilee
can prevent people from being downwardly
mobile and can also help people at least
have more shot more shots at something
like a good life in particular I would
be bullish for the following proposal a
full Jubilee on student debt just full
cancellation of student debt and you
know if you have to if you have to
confiscate some endowments just to make
it sure that the universities don't just
double down and continue gobbling up all
the money that seems fine to me
and this is in a class of people that
has tried to educate themselves and they
were either helped or not helped by the
universities and they suddenly find
themselves free again
so that that I would think is the best
single intervention I can think of in
that space for having there be a leisure
class that can reflect on society yeah
yeah sure some of it was I guess
answered there so I guess in addition to
a depth Jubilee and and it and I and I I
think there's some issues with the ubi
it's just it's just insufficient i I
agree with you it's really only deep not
by the other systems is my point right
yeah it needs other things and it
perhaps needs more stuff let's see my
question up there ok there is yes so
what about as far as increasing the size
of this leisure class I mean I have some
issues with the with the term leisure
because there was I forget who wrote it
there was a book written in the late
19th century about the leisure class and
it's oh yeah that has it in a different
term I kind of used it more in the
Aristotelian sense of leisure ok yeah
because he's using it more in this
elitist you know like the leisure class
was is the elitist class and that the
power elite I'm just proposing you have
unstructured time to pursue on your own
initiative and interest intellectual and
physical self perfection and improvement
right let's say they're Sicilian yeah
yeah which I'm far more Greek than I am
you know in philosophy than I am
in that other sense so I guess that that
whole funding you know how do you how do
you financially support people as we're
moving into this audit automated work
this automated workplace where the whole
goal of automation is to get rid of
people right so that's a that's a
problem we have to you have to face but
citizens assemblies based on sortition I
think is a very key a key part I think
in building up this this Aristotelian
leisure class because people would be
motivated to educate themselves and and
they would have power people would be
chosen by jury from the populace to
actually debate and discuss over-over
issues and and actually pass real
legislation I think that's part of
creating this leisure class I'd like to
know your point of view on that and I'd
also like to know what other ideas
policies or practices or institutions
you think would help to strengthen and
broaden this this leisure class that
we're speaking up yeah I think that I'm
assuming that for the purpose of
government oversight was the initial
notion where it's enough to only have
it's enough to have many many people
looking at different aspects of
government and actually understanding
them ideally participating in them
doesn't require absolutely everyone to
do this it's of course positive if
absolutely everyone can have leisure but
just from a structural perspective it's
not actually it's not a necessity for
that goal so the previous one discovered
and describing like institutional
excellence I do think that the positive
role of time of play or time of
education and so on interspersed with
civic activity is very close to say the
ideal of otm which was a term that you
know the Romans used for this kind of
leisure which was the idea that you have
the opportunity to both retreat from
society and then return to participating
in society because by retreating from
society you have time to reflect on your
own social environment you have time to
like read books and so
so it's not just that I'm not obliged to
go to work its I can in fact to take a
break from my normal social
responsibilities but also I can return
to my previous social responsibilities
at the bout the level of authority that
I had previously you'll be very there's
a small element of this preserve in the
academic sabbatical right imagine if you
could take economic or social
sabbaticals in any position in society
that would be very interesting there's
certainly dysfunctional bearings of that
one could implement but I also suspect
you know very functional ones that would
be difficult to abuse or would be abused
in economically irrelevant ways a ways
that like on the margin it doesn't
really matter if we you know are armed
and really indulging them directly now I
think here here's my contrarian position
you know a lot of people imagine that in
the future the robots do all the work
and automation has fully replaced people
I think we are farther away from that
than we would like to imagine here I
would cite a paper by Robin Hanson and
unfortunately forget his co-author on
the spread of automation where behave is
much more like a colonization wave in
the sense that the areas that are best
automated are the areas that are
economically right adjacent to an
already automated system so it's not
like automation goes into areas that
were not automated at all and wipes out
everyone it's more like automation like
incrementally spreads like say like
angle growth or like plant growth right
next to areas that are already automated
the reason is it's much easier to teach
which means how to work with machines
than it is to teach machines how to work
with people or teach people how to work
with machines right so I think that's
the underlying really basic reason and
why I say you know a lot of people who
liked Andrew yang they thought you were
living in a totally different world
where robots are popping up in fields
that had never received any automation
rather than there's an incremental
advance of that frontier we have to
actually figure out what are people
extremely good at because I don't really
think there is a social structure or
social technology
that would allow us to reliably protect
the rights and reliably keep decision
relevant humans if humans have no
irreplaceable function in so as soon as
you can replace a human the political
temptation exists to remove the human so
if we find what people in particular
with humans are very good at we then the
leisure time to perfect that becomes an
investment rather than a drain in the
system and then it becomes politically
harmful not because you're like so you
know not you're not keeping you're not
keeping them leisured because you're so
idealistic you're keeping them leisured
because you have no choice but to keep
them leisure or spending odium right
odium in this way because they actually
are just formidable enough to deny you
this structurally important role in
society and here's another one here's an
interesting one I would propose we are
nowhere near the optimal economic use of
human beings and that we have in fact in
many ways intentionally made them less
useful and are relying on less efficient
systems right so you know I think if we
examine the physical capabilities of
humans or mental capabilities of humans
in particular here there are many things
we could be doing with a different
social structure that would generate
vast wealth or vast like you know
knowledge value that we are not no one
is going to convince me that the debt
system is the correct way for us to deal
with our most educated class of people
where I actually view it as a control
mechanism you know at first we don't let
the masses into the universities now we
let the masses into the universities ah
but there's a trick you're now indebted
so you're still not free right so I
think that actually was an adaptive
cybernetic response from the system
shutting out this larger crowd of people
from being necessary because if you make
them necessary than their decision
relevant right so I hope I hope this was
not too they I actually speaking fairly
precisely here so whenever I hear people
propose
with advancements in technology people
won't be needed for the economy
therefore we might as well treat them
nicely I think we won't treat them
nicely if they're not necessary for the
economy I think if you look at our
economy we only treat nicely the people
who are absolutely irreplaceable it's
not like you know it's not like people
really adore programmers as people right
now or admire them that deeply it's just
that they happen to be economically
replaceable so they are paid well those
really the cities they live in are still
kind of like not great true but you're
making a certain certain assumption in
your analysis that we're sticking with
the same ye'll neoclassical neoliberal
ideology oh I'm gonna say it's it's it's
beyond neoclassical neoliberal you do
have equivalents things to this and say
the feudal system right so like what I'm
saying here it's more like it's more
like realpolitik rather than assuming
that the competition is baked in it's
more that if you want a non-competitive
or a different system it just has to be
politically more robust than the current
model is that the current one that has
to crumble away and yours is like
winning on its own strengths right and I
hope the point I'm making about the
feudal system is like not that the fuel
system is amazing or even better than
the current one in that regard I'm just
saying that that system would also the
logic also applies to that system not
just this one so I'm proposing this is
like there's like a selection mechanism
that's kind of happening on the metal
level with the different social
technologies at play in the world and if
you actually need something that's way
better not necessarily at strict
material accumulation but at least rapid
institutional adjustment okay now that
really went into it but I don't get many
opportunities to answer that question so
I'm very grateful for it and so I want
to take note of the time but we do have
an excellent question in the chat so I
wanted to invite you to answer that
question if you have the time if not
that's totally fine we can wrap up to be
happy to answer one more excellent Oh
would you like to unmute yourself and
ask your question thank you thank you so
much taking my question
so the increasing role of the judiciary
which you mentioned in creasing law
isn't them since us equally Strasbourg
Court or the ECHR which has had
significant influence in law even in
illiberal countries like Turkey and
Russia and similarly Israel had a
judicial revolution in the early
nineties which led to the High Court
becoming in effect Israel's second
legislative chamber Israel is formally a
unicameral but the High Court acts as a
check a check and balance do you see
these developments as endogenous to the
territories in question do they
originate from the American influence or
do international institutions have
independent power to influence systems
of government in this way and what this
mean for countries like Hungary in
Israel where there is the consistency to
remove or sidestep this judicial justice
power well the main difficulties coming
from an internal elites from great
powers or from some form of
internationalism I think it comes out of
a it's it's the answer is mixed some of
these are in fact straightforwardly
things that are a reflection of current
international elites or current dominant
US influence in the Hungary example I
think the growth of judiciary which has
now been I think significantly curtailed
recently was mostly an externally driven
phenomena in Israel I think is mostly an
internally griffon phenomena if you have
a society that's very high in law where
people have a lot of trust in law but
little trust in politicians then judges
will over time slowly morph into
politicians because they will be
executing political stuff under under
the rubric of neutral impartial
interpretation of the law in America I
think we've gone very far in the
direction of the Supreme Court positions
are just considered political positions
like the party affiliation of the judges
is considered the absolutely crucial
thing people debate the compass
of the Supreme Court much as people
might have debated the composition of
Congress in 1850 right so I think in
that way over time this will diminish
the reputation of law as such because
people will come to see law is no longer
the semi objective thing neutral thing
technocratic thing and see it as more
tactical is more opportunistic so I
think even within the international
system centered on the United States and
these like institutions that's going to
happen I think that the court the
Strasbourg the Stratford Court is and
the European Court serve a very good and
positive example overall but in a way
they're relying on a reservoir of like
liberal thinking in Europe so they're
not adding to liberal thinking in Europe
but they are on the basis of this
liberal thinking liberal norms
institutions exporting the effects to
places like Turkey right so it's I think
important to see what's powering the
process and ultimately distribution
channel so I think of them as an
important distribution channel but it's
once the power plant is off like once
the power plant stops operating all the
lights in the town will go out so don't
think it's permanently altering the
societies right and I think you know in
Israel my prediction is in Israel
actually the court will be fairly robust
because I think the intellectual level
of argumentation in the court is
extremely high I think in Europe it will
remain robust but will decrease in
international prestige as the prestige
of Europe decreases and in the United
States I'm not sure whether the Supreme
Court will remain robust like over the
we're talking about over a 30 year time
period right so I'm not expecting
anything weird next year but like again
like this stuff changes very quickly
FDR threatened to tack the Supreme Court
back in the day this could easily be
done by a different president there's
like no limit on how many people you can
add to the Supreme Court so if I
increased if I press a little button and
increase the size of America's Supreme
Court to 50 judges I've actually made it
less powerful because their ability to
call
with each other is diminished and the
power of external stakeholders to come
into it and internally divide it has
increased I also think it can't possibly
handle the load of all the laws that
have to be taken so a lot of them just
fall down to bureaucratic implementation
instead even a Court decision let alone
legislature decision thank you very much
for a question I was very interesting
and here yeah and Ravin thank you very
much for hosting I really enjoy this and
thank you to everyone who participated
ask questions dan I really enjoyed
talking talking to you about some of the
topics you raised as well to have you
here to talk about institutions and the
viability of our civilization so I hope
to have you back here at the stoah and
thank you everybody for your excellent
questions I'm just gonna let everyone
know that we have a couple events coming
up tomorrow we have collective present
saying a practice with real bake at noon
we have swimming in the digital during a
pandemic with Alexander bard implements
the infamous philosopher at 2:30 and
then we have Socratic speed-dating with
me yours truly I will be hosting that at
7:00 and then stoic meaning wave with a
cure the dawn at 8:30 so a lot of things
happening tomorrow so please join us and
thank you all for coming out
you